So originally, the plan was to talk more
about reinforcement learning.
But I thought since I only had one lecture to give,
I think this class would be a little bit
incomplete without saying something about multimodality,
which is so pervasive if you look at all the major models.
So this will be an overview of multimodal models.
Of course, this could be a whole class in itself,
and I'll try to do what I can in one lecture.
OK, so let's dive into multimodal models.
So far in this class, we have exclusively
focused on language models.
And language models are already pretty general.
They give you the ability to go from any piece of text
to any text.
So this could be any language, code, poetry, anything you like,
even, let's say, DNA, for example.
But the world is multimodal.
You have text, you have images, audio, video.
And if you think about a North Star of where we want to be
is what people call omni model, which
is ability to take any combination of these modalities
and output any combination of any of these modalities.
So, for example, I can give you an image and a video
and I can ask a question about the image and the video.
I can generate images.
I can convert the audio into an image.
You can imagine all sorts of different applications
by having an omni model.
So in this class, I'm not going to build up
to a whole omni model.
But I'll give you some of the pieces that at least allow
you to ingest a little bit of images, which we'll mostly
focus on today.
So how do you build such a thing?
Well, this is a weird way to motivate this,
but the reality is that transformers work really well.
And despite the best efforts of people to try other things,
those are across all of these modalities still at scale
the best thing we have.
所以我们必须弄清楚如何使用它们。
而如今，Transformer 是为文本设计的。
所以它们具有这样的特性：它们使用 token。
它们接收一堆 token 作为输入，
然后输出一些 token。
在这里，我扩展了
tokenization 的概念，使其不只是我们
在文本中见过的离散 token，还可以是连续的 token。
你可以把它们看作 token 的嵌入。
关键在于，一个 token
应该表示某种语义单元的信息。
例如，在自然语言中，token 是 subword。
它们有一定意义。
而例如，一个像素本身当然不是
有意义的。
所以我们必须以某种方式把所有东西，
包括音频和图像，转换成离散或连续的
token。
现在请注意，即使是文本，我们也已经不得不这样做了。
在第一讲中，我们讨论了 tokenization。
在那里，这还不算太糟。
我的意思是，我们有一个 BP tokenizer。
你们实现了它。
这没问题。
人们可能会希望有更好的 tokenizer，或者某种
根本不需要 tokenizer 的东西。
但这也不是世界上最糟糕的事情。
现在，对于非文本模态，我们
需要更加绞尽脑汁，弄清楚
BP tokenizer 的等价物是什么，它
能接收一张图像并生成
Transformer 可以消化的东西。
好，所以这里你必须回答两个问题。
一是，对于非文本数据，例如图像或视频
或音频，如何将它们输入到 Transformer 中？
然后如何将它们生成出来？
本讲将主要关注第一个问题。
好，那么让我们回到过去，把时间倒回到 21 年。
所以 CLIP 模型，你们中一些人可能熟悉，
是现代视觉语言模型的许多基础。
And so we can go through this a bit in more detail.
So CLIP stands for Contrastive Language Image Pre-Training.
And a bit of historical context is around
that time GPT-3 had already happened.
GPT-2.
All the language models had already
gone into this foundation model era.
Neovision was still-- there were some efforts,
but traditionally had been based on large annotated data
sets, such as ImageNet, and training models,
such as the ResNet, on these data sets
and doing a bunch of other things, like data augmentation,
and getting really good performance.
And so the researchers at OpenAI were wondering,
is it possible to leverage the large amount of image
and textual captions out there?
So inspired by this idea in language where you could just
scrape the internet, you have all this text, it's very noisy.
But somehow if you train a large enough model,
you can make sense out of this and generate something useful.
So what was the equivalent of that for images?
So as a result, CLIP was born.
And the idea of CLIP is fairly simple and straightforward.
So the idea here is that suppose I give you
a bunch of image-text pairs.
So let's say I give you 32,000 of these.
OK, so what I'm going to do is for each image
I'm going to encode it using an image encoder, which I'll
explain later, into a vector.
So I'm going to have 32,000 of these image encodings.
I'm going to also do the same thing
with the corresponding text.
So that will give me T1 through TN.
So these are the embeddings of the text.
These are embedding of the images.
Now, the objective I want to set up
is that I want the image-- let's take I1.
So I1 is aligned with T1.
So I want this alignment, the dot product between these two
embeddings to be much larger than the dot product between I1
and all the other texts, OK.
And conversely, I also want for this text
to say that this dot product is larger
than the dot product between T1 and all the other images.
So that, in a nutshell, is the CLIP objective.
And you can imagine doing—there's basically
2 times N different softmax classification problems.
So here's the code.
So you get an n by d matrix for the image encodings
and n by d for the textual embeddings.
You normalize and you take this dot product
with some temperature.
And then you compute the cross entropy, OK.
So it's basically a multi-class classification problem,
where the examples are structured in this m by n matrix form.
OK, any questions about that?
All right, so some more details about how CLIP was built.
So where does the data come from?
There are not too many details in the paper about the data.
Roughly, you take a bunch of queries from somewhere
and then you go search online for these
and you mine a bunch of image and text pairs.
And this resulted in 400 million image-text pairs.
The data set wasn't released, but there
was an effort by this paper called
OpenCLIP, which replicated and further extended the CLIP ideas.
So there was a data set called LAION-5B,
which was released 5 billion images
with textual descriptions.
And there was a bunch of processing that happened.
Interestingly, they actually used CLIP for the data filtering
and then train OpenCLIP.
So there's some bootstrapping happening.
But at least this is a model where
you can point to the data set that it was trained
on and the code as well.
So a few other details.
So images come in all sorts of resolutions.
If you find an internet image, it
might be long and skinny or tall—sorry.
Long and skinny or the other way.
So, arbitrary dimensions.
And one thing that you learn about neural nets
is that they don't like things to be dynamic.
They want things to be fixed size.
So there is a somewhat heuristic processing
that happens is they resize the image so that the shorter side
is 336 or whatever target size.
It could be 224 as well.
And then they center crop to get a square.
OK, this is obviously for convenience.
Later, we'll see that you can do better than this.
But this is just for expediency.
And also at this time the CLIP authors
were thinking about ImageNet and classification.
So usually, the object is in the middle
and you're just trimming off some background.
So it doesn't matter too much.
So what is the vision encoder?
So this is the general algorithm.
But I haven't specified what the image and text encoders are.
Yeah.
So the question I think is why they train on image-text pairs
as opposed to images.
So there is a line of work that tries
to encode images into representations
based on data augmentation.
So, for example, if you take an image-- and I think
this idea called SimCLR.
You augment it.
You crop it.
You randomly perturb it.
Rotate it.
And you want to say that that is the same image.
They should have similar embeddings.
And that's useful for low level details.
But the problem is that you won't data
augment your way from one type of dog to another dog.
So by using the text, it gives you
a higher level semantic representations of images.
And, yeah, that's a good question.
And later, we'll see how these semantic representations are
useful if you look at the types of tasks
that people are trying to solve.
OK, so what is the vision encoder that CLIP uses?
They actually experimented with a bunch of different ones,
ResNets and vision transformers, which had just come out.
They found out that vision transformers performed the best.
So when people say CLIP, they usually mean the VIT version.
And so a vision transformer does the following.
So you take an image and you break it up into these patches.
I think the original paper was 16 by 16
and the CLIP used 14 by 14.
But anyway, you have these little patches,
which are basically vectors.
So each patch is in some sense a--
well, a token for this vision transformer.
You add the positional embeddings
just like you would if you were training a language model,
and then you just put it through a standard transformer.
And if you want to classify, then you would--
well, you would usually want to--OK, sorry.
The transformer encoder produces a sequence of vectors.
And the CLIP paper does something a little bit different.
You can average all these vectors.
That gives you a single vector.
But they thought it was better to do attention pooling, which
means that you take the global average of all the activations,
but then you also do another round of attention
with that query against the key and values of each position.
And that gives you another vector,
which is maybe a little bit more informed
rather than just a straight up average.
OK, so that's the VIT.
And the CLIP paper found that the best model is what is called
VIT-L/14.
So to decipher, this is a large VIT.
I think it has 24 layers or so.
Not quite sure about that.
And 14 by 14 patches.
Each patch is RGB, so it has three channels.
And they trained on 336 by 336 resolution images.
Actually, they trained on a lower res
I guess for speed because high resolution images take longer.
And then for the latter part of training,
they train on higher res.
Yeah.
For the position embedding, would it
be more complicated than the task?
For example, task only has [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah, so the question is, can you
be smarter about the positional embeddings
because this is just linear 0 through 9?
I think in this paper, they actually-- in the CLIP paper,
I believe they tried some 2D version of this.
And the one DNA found that it doesn't really matter that much.
I think it's also--
I always have to take these results with the idea
that they're interested in classification in mind.
So for classification, maybe it doesn't matter.
Later, we'll see a fancier positional embeddings
that do take into account the spatial structure.
OK, so the text encoder is a standard transformer.
It's a GPT-2 style transformer since that
was from the same group that developed GPT-2.
And in order to get a single vector out of a sequence,
they prepended BOS and appended EOS.
And then they took EOS, the activation at the highest layer
as the representation of that whole sequence.
OK, so you have the vision encoder.
You have the text encoder.
And then you can do this process to train.
You pick a batch.
You encode all the text.
You decode all the images.
And then you form these two end cross-entropy losses.
And then you go from there.
OK, so the headline result, which
got a lot of people excited about CLIP back in 2021,
is that on the ImageNet benchmark,
zero-shot CLIP outperforms a ResNet that was trained
on 1.2 million ImageNet images.
So if you think about this, 1.2 million ImageNet images,
this was many, many hours of Amazon Mechanical Turk worker
time to do this annotation.
And now you have CLIP that was trained on more organic web
data.
Of course, this was the labor of a bunch of people on the web.
But if you're able to leverage that or existing data already,
then you can just zero-shot it.
And the zero-shot technique is basically
to explain—I don't have slide support here.
But you take an image and then you have a bunch of text.
And then you basically take the dot product
with the various labels and see which one's the highest.
Oh, yeah.
It is.
Sorry.
It is on this part of the slide.
OK, good point.
So this is a zero-shot prediction,
where you take an image and then you—yeah, what I said.
Cool.
Any questions?
Yeah.
Yeah, so the question is if you have a dog
and there's maybe other captions that also have dogs,
would that confuse the model?
In general, this process is going to be noisy.
It's OK if there's another dog because, on average, it's
unlikely that there's always going to be a dog.
Sometimes it's going to be an apple or a cat or something.
But also another point is that these images are basically
scraped from images on the web with textual text next to them
or in the alt image.
And so they're extremely noisy.
There's been studies that look at when
you have a caption of an image, it doesn't necessarily just
Verbatim say what's in the image.
Because if you have an image and it's a dog,
you don't need to say a dog.
So this process is very noisy.
So it's maybe somewhat surprising but also interesting
that it works.
I mean, there was a lot of data filtering that is needed.
So if you take arbitrary images and text on the web,
it's probably going to be way too noisy.
One other thing to note, which relates
to a point I'll come back to at the very end,
is they also try this alternative where
instead of doing this ranking, they can
predict a text from the images.
So they can set an objective where
they try to take the images and predict
the text, either as a bag of words or as a language model.
And they show that maybe, I don't know, somewhat
surprisingly, that if you use a stronger model,
it actually does worse or at least
is less efficient compared to using bag of words, CLIP.
So this is saying that--
I think saying that for actually the representations
that you're trying to learn-- or, again, this ImageNet accuracy.
So it's classification.
Actually modeling the exact token sequences of the caption
isn't so important for getting the rough representation
of the image.
OK, we'll come back to this point at the end.
So what did we learn so far?
So we've encoded images using CLIP.
And it captures the semantics of the image
because it's paired with text.
And generally, text talks about the semantics.
It is important to note that the design decisions here are
based on image classification.
So it's not very fine-grained.
But yet, it's still, as we'll see, serves
as a robust starting point for everything
we're going to do later.
One technical downside of CLIP is that it does require large
batch sizes, like 30,000.
If you have a batch size of 1, clearly, it
doesn't work, or even 10, it doesn't work.
And furthermore, the softmax operation
operates over the full batch.
So it's not really very decomposable.
Whereas if you think about normal language model
training, a batch of examples, all the sequences parallelize
and you just do aggregation at the end.
So this point will be addressed by another paper from Google
that came out called SigLIP.
And so think about this as basically an improved version
of CLIP.
So it stands for Sigmoid Loss for Language Image Pre-training.
And here, the main difference is that CLIP does
multi-class classification.
It says, I have this aligned text and image.
And I'm going to say this is positive against all
the other alternative images or against all
the alternative text.
SigLIP, in some sense, is a lot simpler.
It basically says for any given image text pair,
are they aligned or not?
So if I reference this diagram up here,
it's basically binary classification
where the diagonals are positive examples
and the off-diagonals are negative examples.
That's it.
So here's the algorithm.
You take the embeddings.
You normalize.
You take the dot product as usual.
But now you're forming the labels which are minus 1
on the off-diagonal, and diagonals you have one.
And then you do log_sigmoid.
So the objective is very simple.
Yeah, so the question is, does this
require any sophisticated sampling strategies?
At least in the initial paper, they
were just operating on literally the same type of matrix.
You could imagine, I think you're probably thinking in general
for these contrastive methods.
The negative examples need to be—sometimes
you need to balance the positives and the negatives,
or the negatives need to be like tight negatives
so that you're not biased.
But at least in the initial version,
this was fairly straightforward.
So to speak about the data, this was done at Google.
This was the data set.
They used another paper, which was another language image
model around 2022, which got a WebLI data set with order
billion image text pairs.
They also did some extra work.
For example, images that have text in them.
They did OCR.
And that's another way to form text image pairs
and did some filtering.
This was multilingual.
The main point of this paper was that it was much more
efficient to train than CLIP.
So CLIP was trained 10 days on 256 TPUv3,
and CLIP was five days on 32v4s.
And you might think, oh, v4s actually
should be faster than v3.
In terms of flops per second, they're actually not.
They're better because you can put more of them in a pod
and the interconnect is better.
But at this scale, it's really actually not faster.
Actually, 60% slower or something.
So the way that this is faster—and, of course,
I think CLIP probably did not try
to optimize the code for the maximum throughput.
It was just let's get this thing to work.
But the SigLIP paper showed that you can parallelize this
as follows.
So you have—basically, if you recall your systems lecture,
so this is you can think about it as DDP if you like,
where each device stores a subset of the image text pairs.
However, there's interactions between the examples,
unlike in language model training, where everything just
factors.
So in the first pass, each device
just computes all the losses on whatever image text
pairs it has locally.
And then you send the text.
So basically, device 1 gets T5 through T8.
And now it's able to compute the negatives here.
And then it gets T9 through T12.
So you rotate around until you cover all the off-diagonal block
entries.
Another thing that was nice about SigLIP
is that you effectively decouple batch size from the loss.
Whereas in CLIP, the loss is tied to the batch size.
If you change the batch size, it's a different loss function.
So they were able to experiment with much smaller batch sizes
less than 16K.
And in that regime, it's much better than CLIP
because the loss function, if you
have too many, too small a batch size, it just degrades.
Whereas for smaller batch size for CLIP, you have more variance
but it's the same in expectation.
It's the same loss.
They also say, well, you can go up to much larger batch sizes.
But that doesn't really help.
And we saw that critical batch sizes at some limit.
And 32K was essentially their critical batch size.
OK, so now we have CLIP and SigLIP.
These are image encoders that take an image, in this version,
just a fixed size image, 336 by 336, let's say, and maps it
into a vector, OK, which contains some semantics.
So now let's start building VLMs, Vision Language Models.
And I'm going to talk about two families of models, LLaVA
and Qwen.
The two are very similar in the broad template.
There are some details that are different,
which we'll go through, and the basic idea
is that we're going to take these embeddings
and then just inject them into our language model.
So this is going to be more of a flavor of mid-training
or post-training, where we take an existing image encoder.
We take an existing LLM, and then we're
going to stitch it together rather than training something
from scratch.
So the LLaVA paper came out in 2023.
And this got people excited because around this time,
the closed models, like GPT, I think it was GPT-4,
was able to do visual reasoning.
And they were able to show that they could do
some visual reasoning as well.
It wasn't as good as GPT-4, of course,
but I think it was an open model and people
got to see what went under the hood.
So for VLMs, there's essentially a few pieces here.
There's the vision encoder.
They use CLIP here.
For the text decoder, they use a language model called Vicuna,
which is the first Llama model that was fine-tuned
on some shared GPT conversations.
So these are conversations that people have with ChatGPT
and share them on this website.
I don't think this is up anymore.
So the data that they used was based on MS COCO.
So this was an annotated data set
where they had Mechanical Turk workers go and annotate
a bunch of images with bounding boxes and captions describing
what was in the image.
So they basically synthesized a data set for their model.
So they prompted GPT-4 with the captions or the detected objects
and GPT-4 to generate questions or conversations.
For example, this is an image in the MS COCO data set.
This was an annotated caption done by a human.
And also here is also annotated by a human.
And then you ask GPT-4, generate me a conversation
and you might get a question and an answer.
You might ask GPT-4 generate me a detailed description.
It generates something, I guess, similar to the caption.
And then you can ask GPT-4 to generate complex reasoning.
And it does something like that.
OK, so those are synthesized data, 158,000 examples.
And then they trained a model on this.
So the model-- so they use CLIP, in particular,
the highest performing CLIP version, ViT-L/14.
So 14 by 14 patches.
And then they-- let's just look at this image.
So they take images.
They send it through this vision encoder CLIP.
That gives you a vector.
But this vector isn't really in the same space,
so to speak, as the text.
So then they multiply by a matrix W
to get another vector, which is in the same space as the text
embeddings.
And for text, you basically just use your standard embeddings
to get vectors.
So what's basically happening is that the text gets encoded
into these vectors and the image also gets
encoded into these vectors.
And then this whole sequence of vectors
just goes through a standard Transformer and produces output.
OK, so we're in some sense converting these images
into textual tokens.
So I can leverage the pre-trained language model.
So to train this model, they do it in two stages.
The first stage is that they freeze the vision
encoder and the language model and only train this matrix W.
And this is what they call the alignment phase, which
is essentially making sure that the image gets
mapped into the same space.
Because if you just use a random W,
these images are not going to be--
I mean, certainly, they're not embeddings,
representing any natural language token.
So the goal of training W is that they
look like natural language token embeddings.
And the second stage is that they now
still freeze a vision encoder and then train
W and the language model.
So they're fine-tuning the language model on their data.
So remember, their data is basically here's an image
and here is a conversation or a description
or a complex reasoning example.
So this is all image plus text to text.
OK, so this is one example from their paper.
It's interesting.
So you have an input image and a conversation.
The user says what's unusual about this image.
And their model is able to tell you that you don't usually
iron on the back of a minivan.
And they also make a point that their model is pretty good
because even if your user prompt is not really
prompting the unusualness, it still talks about it, whereas--
GPT-4, obviously, is able to do this,
but other models at the time were not able to.
OK, any questions about LLaVA?
OK, so that was 2023.
And I'm going to skip forward to LLaVA OneVision, which is 2024.
There is a sequence of papers after the LLaVA paper came out
of LLaVA 1.5, LLaVA-Next.
But I'll capture all of these innovations, I think,
in what I'll describe next.
The main thing that they did is it's essentially
the same recipe, but they are trying
to be more ambitious in terms of the types
of multimodal applications they could do.
So they were able to handle multiple images and videos.
So here's the same diagram.
Now they can take a single image or multiple images
or a video, which is essentially a sequence of images
corresponding to a sampling of the frames.
And here are the vision encoder.
They upgrade it to SigLIP.
The text decoder, they use Qwen-2 now,
which was probably the best language model
that was out at that time.
And then for the projector or the adapter, which
is the thing that takes the output of the vision encoder
and turns it into the input of the language model
is a two-layer MLP instead of a linear projection.
OK, so it's like you have a system
and you're just upgrading the parts.
But it's the same rough system.
So let's talk a little bit about data processing.
So one thing that they wanted to do is to do OCR.
And the thing with OCR is that you
need to preserve very fine-grained information.
Otherwise, a J looks like an I, and that's not good.
So remember that CLIP resizes and crops to 336 by 336.
And clearly, if you have a document
and you crop to 336 by 336, you can't read it.
So their solution is this idea called
AnyRes, which was actually introduced in the LLaVA 1.5 paper.
And the idea is basically, I mean,
it's fairly straightforward.
You break up an image into multiple pieces.
And the idea is that each piece is the resolution of whatever
the vision encoder is going to take, 336 by 336, for example.
So you're going to code all the pieces into a bunch of vectors.
And then you concatenate the vectors.
OK, so you're basically noticing that your vision encoder
can't handle high resolution.
So rather than downsampling, you're
just going to crop and look at different parts of image.
And now if you have really super high resolution images or videos
then, you get too many tokens.
So then they downsample.
But the idea behind AnyRes is that it's adaptive.
And this is nice because the transformer is already adaptive.
Language can be-- your sentences can be any length
and the transformer already handles that pretty well.
So it turns out images can be any resolution.
So that's picking back on the same dynamic ability.
So here is what they actually do for images here.
So let's say you have this image of a paper.
They do downsample and have one path,
which is basically a downsampled encoding of the entire paper.
But then they break it up into these chunks,
where each chunk is the resolution
that the vision encoder expects, and then encodes each of these separately.
And then you concatenate all these patches.
And if you have too many, then you
reduce the number of patches by interpolation.
OK, so then they're able to handle images, multiple images,
and video.
So you think about, well, all of these
are technically all reducible to images,
but they put their thumb on the scale a little bit
because they want to make sure all the modalities are roughly
comparable.
Because videos can be very long, they
don't want their data set to be dominated
by a bunch of repetitive frames.
So here's what they do here.
So for a single image, they basically
have the full image downsampled and then
a bunch of crops up to N crops there, up to 9.
And if you are presented with multiple images,
then they just use the base resolution.
So if you have a single image, I get
to look at it more carefully.
If I have multiple images, I'm just
going to look at it from afar.
And for video, we're going to use even lower resolution
or fewer tokens to represent each frame because the idea is
that, well, videos can be-- they only use up to 32 frames,
but you start running into context length
problems for viewing.
And later, we'll see how a big part
of being able to handle multimodal
is to deal with longer context.
OK, so the data here that they use is, I would say,
the state of philosophy is they want to curate high quality data
and quantity.
Another way to interpret this is that it's very targeted data.
If you look at many of these, it's very task-based
whether you're doing visual question answering or answering
questions about tables.
So this is definitely post-training territory,
where you're trying to get your model to do these tasks,
and therefore, you create a bunch of these tasks.
And this work is also unabashedly, basically,
distilling GPT-4 models so that they
can get the best performance, which is, I guess, not ideal.
But this is what you do if you don't have an annotation budget.
And so they have single images, multiple images, and videos.
So there's a lot of different pieces.
Some of these are very specific.
You give two images and you're trying to spot the difference.
But one thing that--
OK, I'll come back to this at this point later.
So for training, it's roughly the same idea as before,
where the first stage is that you're focused on alignment.
So in particular, you only train the projector,
which is the adapter.
And then in the second stage and the third stages
you train the full model.
And before, we had two stages.
Now, we have three stages.
I'm not sure there's any particular principled reason
for this, except for this second stage is
trying to put high quality data but more focused on knowledge.
And the final stage is focusing on examples that look
like your downstream tasks.
OK, so one thing that they found in this paper, which
was interesting, is that you get transfer between modalities.
So even though they have only single image data
for diagrams and charts, but this actually
generalizes to multiple images.
So at training time, you never saw an example
where you have a table and a chart
and you're asking questions about it.
But at test time, you have two images, one for the table
and one for the chart.
And you're able to have some of conversation about it.
At training time, you only have OCR data on single image data,
and you only have relational reasoning from multiple images.
But you can generalize to these cases which
are useful for powering GUI agents,
where you show it a bunch of screenshots.
This is multiple images and it can generate a description
of the screenshots.
Another example is that they have
this idea of visual prompting, where
you have this circle, which is a part of the image,
but that's meant to highlight the part of the image
that you're supposed to do something about.
And this type of data only exists for single images.
And now it can generalize to videos
where the user says describe the player highlighted in the video.
And this player is across multiple frames.
So when you first look at this and say, oh, boy.
You're basically targeting each of these tasks.
It's supervised learning.
But if you have enough tasks, these models
seem to do some transfer, which is, I guess, reassuring.
OK, so again, this is a fairly standard VLM
template, vision encoder plus the projector into the language
model.
There's a lot of work that goes into the data curation.
They lean pretty heavily into synthesizing task-specific data.
The nice thing about the LLaVA series
is that it's one of the few works that open sources.
They're not just the model weights, but also the data.
So you can really replicate and study this stuff.
OK, now let's talk about the Qwen Models.
So Qwen started also training in 2023 multimodal models.
So the first version was Qwen-VL.
And hopefully, I'll go through this
quickly because you hopefully see the pattern.
The vision encoder, they use OpenCLIP.
Remember, OpenCLIP was the open reproductions of the CLIP model.
So it's basically a CLIP encoder.
And for the adapter, they did one layer of cross-attention,
incorporate 2D positional embeddings and maps to a fixed
size of 256, which is a little bit--
I guess this will be changed later because this is definitely
not very dynamic, but neither is the vision encoder
at this point.
I guess this got cut off.
But the special tokens, they have
an image tag and a box tag for bounding box,
and a ref tag for descriptions.
This is what happens when your slides are in HTML.
So for training, they have three stages, just
like with the LLaVA models.
In the first stage, the idea is to--
I mean, they call it pre-training but you're not
pre-training from scratch.
This is generally large-scale, low quality data.
They freeze the language model and train
the vision encoder and adapter.
So this is a bit different from the LLaVA models, in
that, they train the vision encoder at this point.
And you can see some of the data sets that they are training on,
1.4 billion examples.
Stage 2, they move to higher quality task-specific data.
And you can see some of the usual suspects of VQA data sets,
chart question answering, and so on.
And then they train all the parameters here.
And finally, stage 3 is instruction tuning data.
You freeze the visual encoder and you train the adapter
and the language model.
Here are some examples of the type of things
that they're able to do.
So, of course, this is Qwen.
So some of these examples are in Chinese.
Their interest is also making a model
that is supposed to be subsuming a language model.
So a language model can do code.
So we want the vision model to be good at code as well.
And you can have this example, if you can see it, is an image.
And can you find Spider-Man and the Hulk.
And it can output bounding boxes as well.
It doesn't actually output an image.
It just outputs a bounding box.
And then you can do OCR.
You can compare-- so usual stuff.
OK, so then Qwen-2 was, again, an upgrade.
There's some new ideas here, which I'll go through.
So use a larger vision encoder.
They also started doing dynamic resolution.
I think this was the main thing.
We remember when we went from LLaVA to LLaVA OneVision,
they realized, oh, we need to handle
images of different sizes.
And if you try to do video, it's clear
that you need some dynamic resolution.
So the model is basically-- so let's say you have this picture
here, that might be mapped to 11,000 tokens.
This tiny picture of an equation might be only mapped to 8 tokens
and so on and so forth.
So how do they do this?
Well, basically each-- it's the same idea AnyRes idea
from LLaVA, where each 224 by 224 patch is encoded with a ViT.
And remember the ViT that they started
with is the OpenCLIP bit.
But this gets fine-tuned.
And then trying to reduce the context size,
they compress every 2 by 2 into 1
so that they ultimately each every patch generates 66 tokens.
For eight videos, they sample 2 frames a second but max out
at 16,000 tokens.
OK, so one thing coming back to this question
about positional embeddings, so they did
do something different here with Qwen-2.
So they used this idea called multimodal rotary, multimodal
RoPE.
So remember, we saw RoPE before.
And the idea behind RoPE is that you have embedding such
that the inner product between the vectors
depends only on the distance.
So the distance is defined in 1D by just the number of tokens.
You're away from it.
So now, the multidimensional version
is essentially the same thing.
Except for now you have 3D.
So you have height.
You have width and you have time.
So each position, each patch now is a triple
defined by the coordinates.
And then to compute the M-RoPE, basically, for every dimension,
you compute the RoPE and then you concatenate.
So it's a fairly straightforward idea.
Although, later, with Qwen-3, we'll
see how this is actually a bit suboptimal.
So they initialize the language model with--
this is the Qwen-VL model.
So, of course, they're initializing with Qwen.
And then they have three stages of training,
which is very similar to what we did before.
And then they were able to show a bunch
of different capabilities, some video understanding.
It can do math and code, function calling,
and so on and so forth.
OK, so quickly, I'll talk about Qwen-3.
So again, there's a few changes here.
I wouldn't say these are structural big changes,
but they're probably changes that do impact
the quality of the model.
So this is from last year Qwen3-VL report.
And so it's roughly the same diagram here.
I'll point out maybe--I'll come back to this diagram.
I'll go through some of the changes.
So one is that now they're using Qwen-3 models.
They have a series of dense and MoE models.
And the Qwen-3 models are really, really good,
and it really helps the quality of the final model.
One thing that they're invested in is long context understanding.
So their context length can go up to 256K,
which is really important if you're trying to do long video.
Let's talk about the vision encoder.
So they use SigLIP-2, which is basically
an improved version of SigLIP.
It's actually identical architecture,
is designed to be backward compatible.
And then they improved their RoPE.
And the way to explain this is, before, you
Had the three dimensions: time, width, and height.
And basically, when to basically allocate
the first block of dimensions to the time,
then the next block to width and the next to height.
And the problem, if you remember RoPE
is that each component represents
a different frequency.
So this would mean that maybe all the temporal dimensions
are low frequency and all the high dimensions
are high frequency.
So they basically interleave them when they realize that.
And now all the axes are exposed
to both low and high frequency.
Another thing they did was explicit video timestamps.
So if you look closely at this--
wait.
OK, this is Qwen-3.
Oops.
So if you look--this is probably a little bit too small.
But before, the timestamp was implicit
in the positional encodings.
Each frame in the video intrinsically
gets a different-- there's a notion of time
just because it's in a different position.
But here, they made the time explicit.
So these are actually tokens: zero seconds
is a token--now you have a token that
represents the time.
And they found this to be helpful, presumably because it's
something that you can directly refer to,
like what happened after two seconds.
So that is one of the main changes.
They also did this square root normalized per token loss.
So the idea is that some examples that
involve video are very long and some examples that involve
a single image are very short.
And the normal thing is that every token is treated the same.
And this would mean that the video examples
are going to dominate.
So they basically-- the details aren't too clear.
But I believe they normalized each example
by the square root of the length to basically downweight
the impact of really long examples.
The final thing that is worth noting, which is interesting,
is that they did something interesting with adapter.
So remember we started the adapter is
the thing that connects the vision encoder to the language
model.
And LLaVA was the simplest.
It was just a linear projection.
And then we got an MLP.
And then we got some cross-attention.
And DeepStack, which is actually a paper from the DeepSeek team,
but when used here is more sophisticated.
They noticed that, well, the vision encoder already computes
a stack of vision embeddings.
And we're basically going to basically add
these directly into the residual stream of the language model.
OK, so this is a bit more of a deep fusion of the vision
encoder into the language model as opposed to the vision encoder
is a black box that just outputs a sequence of vectors.
OK, so training is--so they have two phases.
Pre-training has actually four stages.
Post-training has three stages.
So you can see that this pipelines are
getting quite complicated now.
So they first train the adapter.
This is the same as all of these models.
And then they have three stages where they progressively train
on longer and longer sequences, from 8K, to 32K, to 256K.
Most of the tokens are in the stages 2 and 3.
And then for post-training, they do
SFT on long chain of thought data, knowledge distillation,
and then some reinforcement learning.
At this point, it's really a systems paper.
There's a bunch of--I highlighted the core new ideas,
but there's a lot of details that are different.
And if you look at the final results,
this is a pretty good model.
I mean, if you look at these benchmarks as compared
to the closed models Gemini, GPT-5, and Opus 4.1,
these numbers are--
the bold means that it's the best number in that row.
So the Qwen models are actually quite strong.
OK, maybe the-- yeah, a question.
Yeah, so the question is what about video generation
and how do you know whether there should be a video or text?
So first of all, these models don't generate videos or images.
All the multimodal stuff is on the input side.
You're always generating text.
And then you're always in most of these stages, except for RL,
you're supervising every token.
So there's no LLM as a judge or quality on how well
the description is working.
It's just basically whatever is in your data set.
Now, with RL, you can play around with different rewards.
Yeah.
I'll ask is the training of multimodal models
harder than training a pure LLM from a system perspective?
Yeah, so the two questions are trained multimodal models harder
on the system side?
And, I mean, certainly, it's not easier.
I think you pointed out that the data sets are larger.
Video data is just-- even loading it can be a bottleneck.
Whereas generally, we have not really
focused on data loading for talking about language models
because it's very, very cheap.
So that needs to be taken into account.
And all the same principles of making sure
that your data loading is happening
async with actual computation needs to be taken into account.
And the second part was--
sorry, what was the second question?
Oh, yeah.
So the videos and images can have more-- especially
video have more tokens.
So that's one reason we saw this normalization
to make sure that we're not giving more weight to video.
I mean, you can always down weight.
So if you have more tokens, if you don't like that,
you can down weight.
We talked in the last or two weeks ago about data mixtures.
So you can always weight things according
to whatever makes sense.
But there's also a lot of text tokens out there.
So I think, in general, if you look at, yeah,
the models are trained on tens of trillions of tokens.
I think there's a-- yeah, I wouldn't
say that the number of multimodal tokens
vastly outnumbers text tokens.
Yeah, oh, I think you were first.
So the question is, when you do this alignment,
how does it know what the language-- is the model language
model pre-trained?
And it definitely has to be pre-trained because otherwise it
doesn't make sense to align it.
So the language model is frozen.
And you're just training the adapter
to connect the given vision encoder with a given language
model.
And the way you train it is, well,
you pick a token budget, 67 billion tokens
and you just train.
There's not an adaptive threshold here.
Yeah.
Yeah, so the question is, is the number
of parameters in the vision encoder much smaller?
And the answer is yes, in general.
I'm trying to find--where is the other place I--
not here.
OK, the reason is that the vision encoder
is in some sense doing a very local operation.
It's looking at a patch.
A patch is very small.
And it's just trying to understand the patches.
There's not much knowledge.
So the patch, we're not reasoning.
So most of the capabilities of the model
are still in the language model.
I'm trying to find the--OK, where?
Maybe it was up here.
OK, I can't-- oh, yeah.
So if you look at the LLaVA model, so the full--
so 72 billion parameter language model.
Sorry.
What-- OK, I don't know why this number is so-- oh, sorry.
This is 72 million, OK.
So this is much smaller.
The projector is much smaller.
And the ViT is generally less than a billion parameters.
Yeah, I guess mostly because it's fairly a local operation.
I guess that's the easy way to say it.
OK, I'm going to think some other questions.
I'm going to try to move on now.
So Qwen-3 is the last vision language model.
I'll talk about this SOTA, Save Our Performance.
There's a lot of data work that happens.
Not too many details about the data
and the data mix in these later Qwen models.
So you'll have to look at the LLaVA paper or the--
AI2 has a [INAUDIBLE] paper, which
I didn't get a chance to talk about that
has more details here.
And from Qwen to Qwen-2, Qwen-3, many of these changes were
mostly--there's some changes there.
But the overall framework remains the same.
And mostly, it's scaling up, curating more data sets,
noticing that your context isn't-- you have to handle long
context and maybe sharpening your image processing and so on.
OK, so I'm going to now jump to something quite different.
So there's this paper called Chameleon from Meta in 2024.
So, so far, VLMs encode images into these vectors
and then they inject them into a language model.
And because it's a language model,
you can only generate text.
You can't generate images.
So there's many ways you can go about fixing this.
You can just take a VLM.
You can also attach a diffusion head.
And now you can generate images or—
but I want to talk about this idea here,
which is Chameleon says, what if we mapped everything
into discrete tokens?
And in some ways aesthetically this is—
well, maybe this reflects that I'm a language person.
This is appealing because now you can analyze and generate
images in the same way.
Everything is a discrete token.
If you want to do what—
let's say you want to generate images.
You can say, here's a text prompt.
And then you can just— these are more just
tokens that you can generate.
Or you can flip the language and the text around as well.
They have these examples from the Chameleon paper
you can prompt in say I'm bored.
Can you show me some birds?
And then it would be text, and then it
would be images, and then some more text and some images.
So it's interleaved.
So in some sense, the vision of an omni model
is that text and images truly live in the same space.
And this is accomplished by making everything look like text.
That's one way to do it.
OK, so I'll talk a little bit about how this is done.
So the thing you need to do now is to map images
into discrete tokens.
So there's this idea rather old from Oord 2017,
which is called vector quantized variational autoencoder.
And the basic idea here is to map an image
into a discrete code.
And what you learn is a mapping that maps this
into a continuous vector.
And this gets rounded to the nearest code.
So you have a codebook which has, let's say, 8,000 codes.
So these are prototypical vectors that correspond to what
patches.
And then so you pick one of these that's the closest.
And that would be your representation.
So that's your encoder.
It goes through a continuous phase
and then you round it to the nearest code.
And now the decoder is you take that code
and you try to reconstruct the image.
And then you train these VQ-VAEs by basically minimizing
the reconstruction loss.
There are some other terms that you
add because this is not differentiable, which
I won't have time to get into.
OK, but, at the end of the day, you have 512 by 512 images that
are converted into 1,024 tokens, and each token comes from
a vocabulary of 8,000.
OK, so now you have basically text.
You have your images, which are basically these codes.
They train a new tokenizer because now you
have different-- your data looks different than if it were
just normal natural language.
The training is now actually very straightforward.
This is just normal language model training.
There's no adapter.
There's no turn the vision encoder.
There's just a language model now.
So this is the part that's appealing.
So there's still two stages.
But even for language model training,
there's usually two or more stages,
where the first stage is the bulk of training.
It's largely unsupervised.
They have both text and text and image.
And then stage 2, they mix in high quality data.
OK, so this is really great and elegant.
There's a few problems with this.
One is that they found that the training was not stable.
And the reason is that text and images,
despite occupying the same space,
just behave very differently.
So just calling things discrete tokens
isn't hiding the fact that there's an image living there.
And in particular, text tokens, if you
think about predicting the next word,
this has relatively lower entropy.
Most words are predictable, whereas image tokens
have very high entropy.
I don't know what shade of blue this exact token is going to be.
And so as a result, they found that training with this mixture
led to a lot of the norms of the parameters
to grow and to generate loss instability.
They were able to mitigate or fix this
to some extent via QK norm and z-loss regularization, which
controls the norm growth.
So I'm not even going to show the results.
But I wanted to highlight this work because there's
a certain elegance here because it's just one model that treats
really all modalities the same.
But the downside is that it turned out
this model was not really as performant,
and the discretization does definitely lose its information.
So think about OCR.
Again, if you discretize very small print,
you're not going to be able to read it anymore.
And finally, training with multi modalities is also tricky.
We saw this a little bit with the Qwen models
and we had to play around with the weights.
But this is more exacerbated here.
So VQ-VAEs were popular for a while.
And in fact, many people were using this for image generation.
The main reason to do that is, well, you have a transformer.
How do you generate from a transformer?
Well, you have to generate discrete things
and you basically put all your data into this discrete form.
But then diffusion models came out
and became popular and viable for generation.
So this flavor of method is less popular than it used to be.
OK, so maybe just reflect and summarize here.
Frontier models these days are expected
to be multimodal or even more strongly natively multimodal
or omni models.
Unfortunately, I think when Gemini comes out
or GPT comes out, they tout or touted
as being natively multimodal and handle all these modalities.
And in fact, they do.
But of course, there's no details about how these are built.
I think that it's probably combination
of having a continuous encoder because you don't want
to lose information and then diffusion for the generation
because-- but that's my speculation.
The fundamental challenge, I think,
when you're dealing with multimodality
is how do you handle non-text modalities?
It's also interesting that there's
a asymmetry between understanding the modality
and generation.
And there's no one universal encoder let's say.
For example, when we looked at CLIP,
you only cared for classification
to capture high level semantics.
So these vectors could be fairly small
and capture the high level semantics.
Whereas if you wanted to do OCR or whether you wanted
to generate an image, then you need really fine-grained detail.
You need to-- that's why diffusion is so good because it
can really micro optimize the low-high frequency information.
I think, in general, when you're dealing
with multiple modalities, you have to think carefully
about weighing them properly.
For example, video certainly has lower information density
than text.
So you don't want a video to overwhelm your text.
And like I said before, at least the current best thing
is having continuous encoders.
It seems even CLIP, even though it's five years old,
or similar ideas are still the go-to way
to capture semantics of images.
Transformers are still there.
And then diffusion models, which I didn't talk about,
are great for generation.
OK, so I will stop there.
That's it for the lecture on multimodality.
I guess we don't have any homework on doing this.
But if you're curious, I think I encourage
you to play around with training some of these models.